<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>will wolf</title><link href="https://cavaunpeu.github.io/geopolitics/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://cavaunpeu.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://cavaunpeu.github.io/geopolitics/</id><updated>2020-03-12T08:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Soft Power in the Age of Generative Models</title><link href="https://cavaunpeu.github.io/geopolitics/2020/03/12/soft-power-in-the-age-of-generative-models/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-12T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-12T08:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Will Wolf</name></author><id>tag:cavaunpeu.github.io,2020-03-12:/geopolitics/2020/03/12/soft-power-in-the-age-of-generative-models/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What happens when a post-Trump, reputationally-bruised United States, and improved generative models (the technology behind "deepfakes") collide head-on?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nations exert influence in two key ways: hard power, and soft power. Hard power is &lt;a href="https://www.history.com/topics/world-war-ii/bombing-of-hiroshima-and-nagasaki"&gt;dropping the atomic bomb&lt;/a&gt; on Hiroshima and Nagasaki during World War II, compelling the Japanese to surrender. Conversely, soft power is building American libraries in foreign universities, placing American films in foreign theaters, and sending &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peace_Corps"&gt;United States Peace Corps&lt;/a&gt; volunteers to rural communities worldwide, compelling a favorable image of our country abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, hard power is to influence via economic and military violence; soft power is to influence via &lt;em&gt;attraction.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Soft power through media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key subset of soft power is that delivered through media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, during the Franco-Prussian War, the French dropped leaflets over enemy territory by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airborne_leaflet_propaganda"&gt;airborne balloon&lt;/a&gt; touting the mutual benefits of ceasefire. During World War I, all parties dropped such leaflets by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airborne_leaflet_propaganda#First_World_War"&gt;airplane&lt;/a&gt;. In World War II, the Nazis pioneered the use of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio_propaganda#Nazi_Germany"&gt;radio&lt;/a&gt; as a propaganda machine. Finally, in 1969, the Americans live-broadcast Neil Armstrong’s moon landing to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cwZb2mqId0A"&gt;television&lt;/a&gt; screens worldwide, showcasing the "derring-do and genius of American ingenuity, and putting one over the Soviets at the same time."&lt;sup id="fnref-7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-7"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, such media is more numerous and diverse: American shows on Netflix, American music on Spotify, American “influencers” on YouTube, Hollywood movies and more—all distributed globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The cost of media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of media can be split into two broad camps: creation and distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the days of leaflets by balloons, the marginal cost of distribution has become extremely cheap. Today, Trump tweets, and his words instantaneously appear on the timelines of his 75 million followers. Were he to have 150 instead, the additional cost of reaching these additional 75 would be, practically speaking, nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the creation of this media itself remains a wholly manual exercise. To create a news broadcast, humans write scripts, set the stage, select the costumes, apply makeup, and read the news itself. Furthermore, creating twice as many news broadcasts costs, crucially, roughly twice as much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dwindling marginal cost of its distribution makes soft power media efficient and appealing. However, it is the “creation bottleneck” that stands in the way of true scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Generative models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generative models are those that empower &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deepfake"&gt;“deep fakes.”&lt;/a&gt; They are algorithms that generate realistic &lt;a href="https://thispersondoesnotexist.com/"&gt;images&lt;/a&gt; (refresh this link for more), &lt;a href="https://medium.com/syncedreview/deepmind-dvd-gan-impressive-step-toward-realistic-video-synthesis-12027d942e53"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://openai.com/blog/musenet/"&gt;audio&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://talktotransformer.com/"&gt;text&lt;/a&gt;, or other types of rich media. Presently, generative models excel in creating art, music, literature, news reports, and textiles. &lt;a href="https://news.microsoft.com/apac/features/much-more-than-a-chatbot-chinas-xiaoice-mixes-ai-with-emotions-and-wins-over-millions-of-fans/"&gt;Microsoft’s Xiaoice&lt;/a&gt;, a multi-purpose &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chatbot"&gt;chatbot&lt;/a&gt; (which currently dialogs with over 660 million registered users), pulls all this off and more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Xiaoice’s framework is learning to write literature as well as compose and perform songs. Last year she published a book of poems and helps her followers write their own. She can sing her own songs in styles based on existing popular performers. There are plans to release an album of pop tunes soon. And she is able to author tailor-made stories for children and reads them out in voices suited to each of the characters she has created.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;She’s painting images based on keywords and other inputs. She’s also gone into mainstream media as a host of dozens of TV and radio programs that are broadcast across China. She reads news stories and provides commentary. And, she is generating multiple reports based on information from China’s financial markets and used by investors and traders who subscribe to Wind, a major financial information service.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In short, generative models &lt;strong&gt;automate&lt;/strong&gt; the creation of media itself—smashing the “creation bottleneck” outright.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coming soon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, generative models succeed at tasks like: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PCBTZh41Ris"&gt;transferring dance moves&lt;/a&gt; from professionals to amateurs, &lt;a href="https://github.com/elliottwu/sText2Image"&gt;translating pencil sketches&lt;/a&gt; to high-resolution images with the guidance of text, and making Obama lip sync the words of American actor Jordan Peele.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cQ54GDm1eL0" title="Click me!"&gt;&lt;img alt="Click me!" class="img-responsive" src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/cQ54GDm1eL0/0.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These feats are impressive. However, to achieve widespread impact, these algorithms must allow for more “control” over the media they create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, consider a system that, given English text, instantaneously generates a video of this text being recited in an arbitrary language. To be truly effective as a soft power tool, this system must ultimately operate as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System&lt;/strong&gt;: “What kind of video would you like?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User&lt;/strong&gt;: “I’d like a video of the President reciting the uploaded text. I'd like him to speak slowly, be wearing green US Army fatigues, and be seated in front of a blue Boeing CH-47 Chinook. Make me two, actually: one in Farsi, the other in Greek.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System&lt;/strong&gt;: “Coming right up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Such generative models are not quite here. However, given the speed at which this &lt;a href="http://www.arxiv-sanity.com/search?q=video+generation"&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; moves, they will reliably arrive within 5 years.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The United States used to invest in soft power institutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, the United States invested substantially in soft power institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During World War I, Woodrow Wilson established the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committee_on_Public_Information"&gt;Committee on Public Information&lt;/a&gt;, which ultimately trafficked in outright propaganda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During World War II, Roosevelt established the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_diplomacy_of_the_United_States"&gt;Division of Cultural Relations&lt;/a&gt; and Office of Inter-American Affairs in response to fascist propaganda in Latin America. Following the bombing of Pearl Harbor, the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voice_of_America"&gt;Voice of America&lt;/a&gt;—a globally-distributed radio broadcast of non-military promotional content—the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Office_of_War_Information"&gt;Office of War Information&lt;/a&gt;—distributing media like “newspapers, posters, photographs, films”&lt;sup id="fnref-8"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-8"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to civilian communities abroad—and the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_of_Strategic_Services"&gt;Office of Strategic Services&lt;/a&gt;—the predecessor to the CIA—were all established as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Cold War, the United States flexed its “peacetime” soft power muscle, establishing myriad organizations to promote international cultural and educational exchanges, including the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fulbright_Program"&gt;Fulbright Program&lt;/a&gt; in 1947 and the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_diplomacy_of_the_United_States#U.S._Information_Agency_(USIA)"&gt;United States Information Agency&lt;/a&gt; (USIA) in 1953.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dwindling interest and opportunity missed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the Cold War, however, American soft power institutions began to slowly decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1999, the USIA was absorbed into the US State Department; its staff, and budget for key projects, were cut roughly in half.&lt;sup id="fnref-6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; “From 1995 to 2001, academic and cultural exchanges dropped from 45,000 to 29,000 annually, and many accessible cultural centers and libraries were closed.”&lt;sup id="fnref2-6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Finally, “while government-funded radio broadcasts reached between 70 and 80 percent of the populace of Eastern Europe during the Cold War, around year 2000, a mere 2 percent of Arabs heard the VOA.”&lt;sup id="fnref3-6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, the United States has a largely &lt;a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/2017/01/trump-foreign-policy-isolationsim-america-first-allies-nato-trans-pacific-partnership/"&gt;isolationist president&lt;/a&gt; in Donald Trump. Since the beginning of his term, American soft power has fallen globally according to the Portland &lt;a href="https://softpower30.com/"&gt;Soft Power 30&lt;/a&gt;. Trump himself is unconcerned with others actively &lt;a href="https://www.rollcall.com/2018/09/25/world-leaders-laugh-as-trump-boasts-of-accomplishments/"&gt;laughing&lt;/a&gt; at him and his country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2018, Statista estimates that there were 1.67 billion "pay TV households" worldwide.&lt;sup id="fnref-9"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-9"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; By 2019, they estimate that half of private households had a computer.&lt;sup id="fnref-10"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-10"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Finally, Pew Research estimates that "more than 5 billion people have mobile devices, and over half of these connections are smartphones."&lt;sup id="fnref-11"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-11"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_Age"&gt;Information Age&lt;/a&gt;, a dwindling interest in soft power institutions is a &lt;strong&gt;major&lt;/strong&gt; opportunity missed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent article, Joseph Nye, the Harvard professor who coined the term “soft power” itself, neatly summarizes this phenomenon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“U.S. President Donald Trump’s administration has shown little interest in public diplomacy. And yet public diplomacy—a government’s efforts to communicate directly with other countries’ publics—is one of the key instruments policymakers use to generate soft power, and the current information revolution makes such instruments more important than ever.”&lt;sup id="fnref-4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A renewed interest in soft power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly impactful generative models, and Trump’s exit from office, will soon collide head-on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, the United States—with its blemished reputation, exorbitant military budget&lt;sup id="fnref-12"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-12"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, longstanding technical leadership&lt;sup id="fnref-13"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-13"&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and forever proactive drive—will be sitting on transformative media tech and a clear-cut mission: rebuild its image at home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To this effect, I predict that the United States will soon make a concerted investment in generative models for soft power at true scale.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what this might look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Soft power through media, in the age of generative models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two keys areas which generative models will impact are state-to-public, and state-to-individual media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;State-to-public media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current examples of state-to-public soft power media, like Presidential addresses to the American people, English-language CNN news broadcasts to foreign viewers, and front-line conflict reporting will see their use both quickened and expanded by generative models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presently, Presidential addresses happen once every few weeks or months. Conversely, Donald Trump writes on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; hourly. With generative models, the next President will &lt;em&gt;instantaneously&lt;/em&gt; generate videos of herself reciting the tweet instead. Americans at large devour the President's tweets; if a generated video legitimately looks and sounds just like her, they’re likely to devour it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sponsorship deals, like &lt;a href="https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/14314807/lebron-james-signs-life-deal-nike"&gt;Lebrons’ lifetime appointment&lt;/a&gt; with Nike, will crucially expand to include the right to generate content with the athlete’s likeness. Politicians will travel less to campaign; instead, they’ll send generated holograms—of them, their spouses, their key supporters—to campaign instead—each one personalized to the venue in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a generative model will be trained to ingest footage of world events—for example, the &lt;a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/09/14/middleeast/yemen-houthi-rebels-drone-attacks-saudi-aramco-intl/index.html"&gt;attack&lt;/a&gt; on the Saudi oil refinery—and produce text describing what happened. This text will then be used to generate a news report. Humans won’t be on the front line to capture this footage either; why not send a drone instead?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;State-to-individual media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft’s Xiaoice demonstrates the enormous traction of personalized chatbots. From here, the jump to state-built, propaganda-(subtly)-infused chatbots is small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the public distrusts governments; to this effect, humanitarian missions are typically run by NGOs. As such, states will deploy these chatbots on behalf of related entities: tourism boards, online universities, cultural centers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, current state-to-individual media is largely &lt;em&gt;unidirectional&lt;/em&gt;: media is sent from the former to the latter, and rarely vice versa. Chatbots powered by generative models, however, will solicit &lt;em&gt;feedback&lt;/em&gt; from their viewer in a personalized way; for example, “Are you enjoying this media? What do you like about American schools as compared to your own? What do you think about democracy?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same way that the Chinese government &lt;em&gt;passively&lt;/em&gt; learns about its citizens by &lt;a href="http://harvardpolitics.com/world/wechat-the-people-technology-and-social-control-in-china/"&gt;monitoring WeChat data&lt;/a&gt;, generative models will &lt;em&gt;actively solicit information&lt;/em&gt; re the efficacy of their soft power plays. Then, like a savvy marketer, they’ll double down on the stuff that works best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a century, states have exercised soft power through media. Throughout, the marginal cost of distributing this media has trended towards zero. Conversely, to date, the marginal cost of its creation remains high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generative models are a powerful technology which trend the latter towards zero as well. They're here and they work. However, to be truly impactful, there's still a short ways to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 5 years' time, a dazed, reputationally-bruised United States, and robust, flexible, practical generative models, will collide head-on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At this point, soft power media—and human politics in general—are likely to change forever.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Credit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to Abishur Prakash for reviewing earlier drafts of this piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brands, Hal. “Not Even Trump Can Obliterate America's Soft Power.” Bloomberg.com, Bloomberg, www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2018-01-18/not-even-trump-can-obliterate-america-s-soft-power. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chakravarti, Sudeshna. Soft Power: The Culture Weapon in The Cold War and South Asia. www.culturaldiplomacy.org/academy/content/pdf/participant-papers/academy/Sudeshna-Khasnobis-Soft-Power-The-Culture-Weapon-in-The-Cold-War-and-South-Asia.pdf. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khandelwal, Aakash. “Economics of Digital Goods.” LinkedIn SlideShare, 23 Nov. 2016, www.slideshare.net/aakashkhandelwal921/economics-of-digital-goods. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nye, Joseph S. “No, President Trump: You've Weakened America's Soft Power.” The New York Times, The New York Times, 25 Feb. 2020, www.nytimes.com/2020/02/25/opinion/trump-soft-power.html. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shah, Ritula. “Is US Monopoly on the Use of Soft Power at an End?” BBC News, BBC, 19 Nov. 2014, www.bbc.com/news/world-29536648. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nye, Joseph S. Soft Power: the Means to Success in World Politics. Knowledge World, 2012. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2-6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref3-6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harris, Paul. “Man on the Moon: Moment of Greatness That Defined the American Century.” The Guardian, Guardian News and Media, 25 Aug. 2012, www.theguardian.com/science/2012/aug/25/man-moon-american-century. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-7" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“United States Office of War Information.” Wikipedia, Wikimedia Foundation, 7 Jan. 2020, en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Office_of_War_Information. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-8" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watson, Amy. “TV Households Worldwide.” Statista, 4 Dec. 2019, www.statista.com/statistics/268695/number-of-tv-households-worldwide/. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-9" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-10"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statista Research Department. “How Many People Have Access to a Computer 2018.” Statista, 2 Mar. 2020, www.statista.com/statistics/748551/worldwide-households-with-computer/. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-10" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-11"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silver, Laura. “Smartphone Ownership Is Growing Rapidly Around the World, but Not Always Equally.” Pew Research Center's Global Attitudes Project, Pew Research Center, 30 Dec. 2019, www.pewresearch.org/global/2019/02/05/smartphone-ownership-is-growing-rapidly-around-the-world-but-not-always-equally/. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-11" title="Jump back to footnote 11 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-12"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cancian, Mark F. “U.S. Military Forces in FY 2020: The Strategic and Budget Context.” U.S. Military Forces in FY 2020: The Strategic and Budget Context | Center for Strategic and International Studies, 12 Mar. 2020, www.csis.org/analysis/us-military-forces-fy-2020-strategic-and-budget-context?gclid=CjwKCAjwgbLzBRBsEiwAXVIygLkZlNLc3zV8EVVhPPwjOoqrUoQ4kjTeaTHN5vFktRWET2wsnHCwRhoCm2QQAvD_BwE. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-12" title="Jump back to footnote 12 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-13"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Report Shows United States Leads in Science and Technology as China Rapidly Advances.” ScienceDaily, ScienceDaily, 24 Jan. 2018, www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2018/01/180124113951.htm. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-13" title="Jump back to footnote 13 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>On Saudi Drone Strikes and Adversarial AI</title><link href="https://cavaunpeu.github.io/geopolitics/2019/09/22/saudi-drone-strikes-and-adversarial-ai/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-22T08:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-22T08:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Will Wolf</name></author><id>tag:cavaunpeu.github.io,2019-09-22:/geopolitics/2019/09/22/saudi-drone-strikes-and-adversarial-ai/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In world of weaponized drones piloted by algorithms, what new strategic opportunities arise?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, Houthi rebels—a militant political group in Yemen—claimed credit for exploding an oil refinery in Saudi Arabia. The explosion was the work of a missile, fired from a drone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the group responsible is closely allied with Iran—and to wit, the American government does declaim Iran as responsible for facilitating the strike itself—it is by all accounts a non-state actor, notable for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the cost of full-scale war increases due to, at a trivial minimum, the strength of weapons available, small, “surgical” operations become more common. This attack falls in directly with this trend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You do not have to be the state to desire to affect world politics. As weapons become more potent, and the “density” of potential targets—population density, in the case of traditional military offensives, or density of nodes in an information-sharing network, in the case of cyber offensives, as two examples—increases, the ability to affect outsized change increases as well. As such, incentives for, and frequency of, strategic action from non-state actors will likely continue to rise—this being yet another example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The technologies required to effectuate the attack in question are increasingly easy to obtain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, last week’s strike is yet another example of an isolated punch by a non-state actor with technologies (drones, at a minimum) ultimately available in the public domain. Moving forward, it seems safe to expect more of the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enter machine learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout history, much of war has been about destroying the enemy’s stuff. There are many ways to do this—each involving a distinct set of tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this effect, drones are particularly interesting: they allow for precise, close-proximity strikes, without risking the lives of the aggressors. Presently, the majority of such drones are piloted remotely by humans; moving forward, they—in conceptual step with, say, self-driving cars—will pilot themselves, allowing for larger and larger deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, engineers will equip drones with cameras, and machine learning algorithms that make the drone’s operational and tactical decisions conditional on what these cameras show. As such, the defensive objective is still, as per usual, thwart the aggressor; &lt;strong&gt;however, the aggressor is now the machine learning algorithms controlling the aggressor’s tech.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For drones, what do these algorithms look like? How can they be thwarted? What risks and opportunities do they imply for the defense of critical infrastructure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;While these questions might seem futuristic, that future is indeed approaching fast.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The supervised classification model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin the discussion, let’s look at the basic paradigm by which self-driving cars operate: the supervised classification model, which works as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineers collect a large amount of “labeled data” in the form of &lt;code&gt;(cameras_images, what_the_driver_did)&lt;/code&gt; pairs. This data is considered “labeled,” as each input, &lt;code&gt;cameras_images&lt;/code&gt;, is coupled with an output, &lt;code&gt;what_the_driver_did&lt;/code&gt;. An example of the former might be 360-degree images of a curving, barren road in Arizona; the latter, i.e. what the driver did in this moment in time, might be: depress the gas pedal by five degrees, and rotate the steering wheel counter-clockwise by seven.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Teach” a computer to, given photographic input, predict the correct driver action to be taken.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roughly speaking, a self-piloting drone would not be different: it’d require equivalent labeled data from human-controlled flights, on which a supervised classification model would be trained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A likely progression of offensive drone tech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weaponized drone deployment will likely progress as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy drones that pilot themselves; however, “finish” decisions are still executed by humans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy drones that pilot themselves; “finish” decisions are executed by the drone—when it is extremely confident in its choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy swarms of drones that work together to more swiftly and efficiently achieve the aforementioned—attacking, exchanging data, self-sacrificing optimally, etc. throughout their attack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In a brave new world of machine-learned aggressors, what new opportunities for defense arise?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adversarial examples in machine learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adversarial examples for supervised image classification models are inputs, i.e. images, whose pixels have been perturbed in a way imperceptible to a human eye, yet cause the classifier to change its prediction entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example&lt;sup id="fnref-1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; looks as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="png" class="img-responsive" src="https://cavaunpeu.github.io/geopolitics/../images/saudi-adversarial/panda-adversarial-example.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the classifier is 57.7% confident that the image contains a panda; after adding noise, resulting in the image on the right—still, inarguably, a panda, to the human eye—the classifier has now changed its prediction to "gibbon" with 99.3% confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As such, knowledge of the data on which an aggressive drone was trained gives unique opportunity to algorithmically design adversarial examples, like the above, that confuse its classifier aboard.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concrete opportunities would include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At “find”&lt;/strong&gt;: defensive lasers pointed at critical infrastructure dynamically perturb, by just a few pixels, its appearance, tricking the drone into thinking it has not found what it actually has.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At “fix”&lt;/strong&gt;: these lasers dynamically concoct sequences of perturbations, tricking the drone into thinking its target is moving erratically when it’s actually still.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At “finish”&lt;/strong&gt;: adversarial examples make the drone believe its strike would, put simply, cause more damage than it intends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As adversarial examples are, once more, built from real examples, perturbed minimally, in a way imperceptible to the human eye, they are in fact difficult to, even a priori, teach our classifier to ignore. Said differently, well-designed adversarial examples are extremely effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Out-of-distribution data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning algorithms are notoriously bad at “knowing what they don’t know.” Said differently, these algorithms only learn to make decisions about the type of data on which they’re trained. Were a classification model piloting a drone to be presented with an image of an ice-cream cone, it would, barring careful design, attempt to make a decision about this data all the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world of autonomous fly-and-finish drones, one would hope that its finish decisions are taken with extreme care. Fundamentally, this dovetails quickly into the notion of “out-of-distribution” data, i.e. data that the classifier knows it has not seen before, and about which it therefore neglects to make a prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As such, insight into the data on which an enemy’s system was trained naturally implies “defense by what’s different”&lt;/strong&gt;: show the drone images you know that it hasn’t seen before, and thereby increase its uncertainty around the decision at hand—buying time, and keeping your stuff in tact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning optimal defense via reinforcement learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinforcement_learning"&gt;Reinforcement learning&lt;/a&gt;, though exceedingly powerful, and often overhyped, is a relatively simple idea: given an environment and its state, try an action, observe a reward, and repeat the actions that give high rewards; additionally, periodically explore new actions you’ve never tried before just to see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reinforcement learning, or RL, requires vast amounts of data. As such, as a point of “meta defensive strategy”, trying out different types of adversarial-machine-learning attacks against a drone, seeing which work best, then repeating the best performers, while plausible in theory, would not work in practice if one drone approaches your one oil refinery but once a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This said, swarms of drones might change the game; &lt;em&gt;what if, in 20 years, Houthi militants deployed one autonomous, armed drone for every square mile of Saudi territory?&lt;/em&gt; And what if we could simulate this scenario a priori, and learn how to optimally defend against the swarm?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, you'd require:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A heavy investment into sensors&lt;/strong&gt;, on all of: the infrastructure you’re trying to protect, atmospheric conditions in which the drones are flying, tools to monitor the drones’ speeds and movements, etc. In other words, any and all technologies that capture the state of the environment, and the rewards, to as granular level of detail as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simulation environments.&lt;/strong&gt; In certain RL problems, this one potentially included, one has the delicious ability to generate data from which the algorithm can learn—by letting it play games with itself. &lt;a href="https://deepmind.com/blog/article/alphago-zero-starting-scratch"&gt;AlphaGo Zero&lt;/a&gt; is one famous such example. Learning to optimally defend against a swarm of drones might fit the bit as well: deploy thousands of your own into a broad swath of desert, instruct them to “capture your flag”, then let your defensive systems get to work: taking actions, observing the subsequent reward—“Did I divert the drone away from my flag?”; “Did the drone hesitate more than usual before acting?”; etc.—and repeat those actions that work best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the years roll forward, machine learning algorithms will continue to direct more and more of our most critical systems—financial markets, healthcare, transportation, and alas—the offensive technologies of political groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wit, an understanding of the workings of these algorithms sheds light on the new risks these systems will introduce, and the new strategic opportunities that will thereafter arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodfellow, I., Shlens, J., Szegedy, C. (2014). Explaining and Harnessing Adversarial Examples https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.6572 &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Thumbnail) “Adversarial AI: As New Attack Vector Opens, Researchers Aim to Defend Against It.” DataProtectionCenter.com - Tech and Security, 17 Apr. 2018, dataprotectioncenter.com/malware/adversarial-ai-as-new-attack-vector-opens-researchers-aim-to-defend-against-it/. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Artificial Intelligence and Geopolitics</title><link href="https://cavaunpeu.github.io/geopolitics/2019/09/21/ai-and-geopolitics/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-21T21:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-21T21:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Will Wolf</name></author><id>tag:cavaunpeu.github.io,2019-09-21:/geopolitics/2019/09/21/ai-and-geopolitics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm beginning to write about the intersection of artificial intelligence and geopolitics.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Machine learning and artificial intelligence have long been passions; to date, I've spent many years—my entire professional career included—developing relevant expertise. This has been the historical focus of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I've been reading heavily in other areas as well: history, political theory, strategy, economics and geography; geopolitics, in sum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geopolitics of yesterday—the subject of my reading—has its experts and central themes: collective security, nuclear armament, and oil, to name a few. Conversely, the geopolitics of tomorrow will take form from entirely new ideas; chief among them: artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, I plan to merge the two: to suffuse, through writing, my exploration of the former with my expertise in the latter. &lt;strong&gt;Specifically, I'll connect deep, technical knowledge of AI algorithms, as well as the likely implications of their widespread use, to the risks—and opportunities—that AI will bring to the geopolitics of tomorrow.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My writing will be objective, i.e. devoid of overt political bias. My intended audience is non-technical, i.e. geopolitics-first. Your comments—especially with respect to my evolving understanding of geopolitics itself—are encouraged as always.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>