<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>will wolf - geopolitics</title><link href="https://willwolf.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://willwolf.io/feeds/geopolitics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://willwolf.io/</id><updated>2020-08-16T16:00:00-04:00</updated><subtitle>writings on machine learning, crypto, geopolitics, life</subtitle><entry><title>Halford Mackinder on Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="https://willwolf.io/2020/08/16/mackinder-on-ai/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-16T16:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-16T16:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Will Wolf</name></author><id>tag:willwolf.io,2020-08-16:/2020/08/16/mackinder-on-ai/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What would preeminent 20th century geographer Halford J. Mackinder say about the coming revolution in artificial intelligence and its impact on our current ideological war?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halford_Mackinder"&gt;Halford J. Mackinder&lt;/a&gt; was an English geographer, academic and politician. Born in the 1860s and deceased shortly after the end of World War II, he is largely known for a reading at the Royal Geographical Society of his 1904 paper, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.iwp.edu/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/20131016_MackinderTheGeographicalJournal.pdf"&gt;The Geographical Pivot of History&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. In this work, Mackinder describes in sweeping detail the preceding two thousands years of human activity—how geography, along with climate, religion, commerce and war, shaped the world of the time of his writing and facilitated the meteoric rise of the then-dominant Continental European powers. On this foundation, he then delivers, in an inspiring if admonitory crescendo, his famous "Heartland Theory"—a geopolitical analysis of the importance of these powers controlling what is modern Central Asia in the coming (20th) century—for which he is most singularly remembered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this post is to reimagine The Pivot in content and form for the 21st century. First, I'll reintroduce the paper's main ideas. Then, I'll play with the following question: &lt;strong&gt;what might Mackinder write if he were alive today?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Geographical Pivot of History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mackinder begins his famous work by asserting that in 1904, the world stands at the &lt;em&gt;exit&lt;/em&gt; of the Columbian epoch: a 400-year period of European expansionism, in which European states—principally French, Spanish, Dutch, English and Portuguese—sent their generals, scientists and engineers to explore, detail, and ultimately subjugate people and land in the furthest reaches of the globe—transforming themselves from provincial, land-based powers into global empires, now dominant at sea, and transforming the "known world map" from an ill-lit, half-built cabin deep in an unnamed wood to an immaculate Grand Hotel with a different European powerhouse in every single room. As such, in 1904, his continent's powers sat atop a now-familiar world, shoulder-to-shoulder, with nowhere to go but &lt;em&gt;down.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the stage set thus, Mackinder invites us to step back, inhale deeply, and reflect—with a bias towards Continental Europe, no doubt, owing implicitly to its then-dominant stature, and perhaps to Mackinder being English himself—on some of history's broadest currents through the lens of geography: what was, what is, and what will be utterly crucial in the coming 20th century—his "Geographical Pivot."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Continental European landmass comprises an intricate series of mountains, valleys and peninsulas. These features, in turn, provide Europeans with ample physical barriers between which a multitude of politically and culturally distinct nation-states could and did take root. In stark contrast, Mackinder then describes the Russian landmass, one of an altogether different geographic profile: dense mixed and deciduous forest to the North; dry, arid steppe to the South, relatively inhospitable to both life and agriculture; unendingly flat throughout. Unlike Europe, this geography bred a different type of person and society: regional capitals like Kiev, Moscow and Kazan took root just north of this dividing forest-steppe frontier, whereas the sandy steppe itself spawned, well, a thousand years of nomadic invaders—Huns, Avers, Bulgarians, Magyars, Khazars, Patzinaks, Cumans, Kalmuks, Genghis Khan's Mongol hordes, and others—hardened by its brutal conditions, in sync with the land's silent whisper of "keep on moving, life won't survive here."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its first 1,500 years following the death of Jesus Christ, Continental Europe evolved largely on land. Corralled from the West by the Atlantic, as yet uncrossed, the North by the Scandinavian tundra, the South by, in effect, the immense sweep of the then-impenetrable Sahara, and the East by roughly 7,500 kilometers of remaining Eurasia comprised primarily of hostile Central Asian Steppe, separating Berlin from Beijing and the Pacific Ocean. As such, the bulk of Europe's military and political growth remained on its home turf. And implicitly, as the only game in town, &lt;em&gt;land power&lt;/em&gt; reigned supreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the heels of the Renaissance around 1,500 A.D., things changed. Emboldened and energized by cultural and economic development at home, European explorers took to the seas in zealous pursuit of additional sources of wealth and knowledge abroad. In 1498, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasco_da_Gama"&gt;Vasco de Gama&lt;/a&gt; rounded the Cape of Good Hope, traveling directly from Europe to India without traversing the Middle East. In 1492, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Columbus"&gt;Columbus&lt;/a&gt;, the namesake of the Columbian age itself, crossed the Atlantic and reached the Americas. Over the next 400 years, European nation-states swiftly amassed empires of global proportions, subjugating previous inhabitants under their economic, military and political control, and becoming, new in history, the preeminent titans of &lt;em&gt;sea power&lt;/em&gt; throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following map shows European exploration routes during this era. (Though it only covers years 1492-1682, the general trend it shows continued until the time of Mackinder's writing.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="european exploration map" class="img-responsive" src="http://callisto.ggsrv.com/imgsrv/FastFetch/UBER2/00018293"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply, Europeans went everywhere! Except the Russian Empire. Except Mongolia. Except the Central Asian Steppe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1904, following 400 years of global domination, European historians were wont to consider their own stories, self-development and influence as superior to that of others. In response, in his paper, Mackinder implores us to reconsider the map of pre-Columbian Continental Europe, and the ways in which, owing to this map, the development of European society itself was shaped considerably from the &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, until Columbus, the Atlantic Ocean remained uncrossed, thereby serving as an impregnable natural border to the West. Likewise, the menacing infinity of the Sahara to the South remained uncrossed until the mid-19th century. Conversely, the cold and cheerless tundra to the North played host to the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viking_Age"&gt;Viking Age&lt;/a&gt;, a 200-year period of disruption and settlement in and around the North Sea—the British Isles, Ireland, Iceland, Greenland, the Faroe Islands, and others—as well as descents down the rivers Dnieper and Volga wherein the Vikings lived and traded with peoples in Kievan Rus and the Eastern Roman Empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, east of the Carpathians (in present-day Romania), sweeping north-east to the Ural Mountains (approximated by Chelyabinsk, Russia on the map below) then south-east through both Kazakhstan and Mongolia, is, well, what? What protected and will henceforth protect Europe from an intruding Eastern neighbor? On what natural borders can it count? Here, Mackinder (figuratively) smiles, stands up, cooly eyes the crowd, and concludes: "Nothing." Then, he reminds European historians what actually happened before the recent Columbian epoch that has so warped their perception and egos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="central asian steppe" class="img-responsive" src="https://willwolf.io/images/mackinder-on-ai/central-asian-steppe.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, the 5th to 16th centuries saw unending progressions of inveterate Asiatic invaders crossing the ceaseless Central Asian Steppe and &lt;em&gt;hammering&lt;/em&gt; the European land powers like &lt;em&gt;pestle to mortar.&lt;/em&gt; Furthermore, there is evidence that these invasions sparked the formation of many of the modern Continental European states themselves! Mackinder writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large part of modern history might be written as a commentary upon the changes directly or indirectly ensuing from these raids. The Angles and Saxons, it is quite possible, were then driven to cross the seas to found England in Britain. The Franks, the Goths, and the Roman provincials were compelled, for the first time, to stand shoulder to shoulder on the battlefield of Chalons, making common cause against the Asiatics, who were unconsciously welding together modern France. Venice was founded from the destruction of Aquileia and Padua; and even the Papacy owed a decisive prestige to the successful mediation of Pope Leo with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attila"&gt;Attila&lt;/a&gt; at Milan. Such was the harvest of results produced by a cloud of ruthless and idealess horsemen sweeping over the unimpeded plain—a blow, as it were, from the great Asiatic hammer striking freely through the vacant space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, though European society had matured significantly in the preceding 2,000 years, evolving from land-based principalities to sea-faring, nation-state empires of global reach, its &lt;em&gt;geography&lt;/em&gt; had, and will always, stay the same. In 1904, transcontinental dominion notwithstanding, the Steppe to Europe's East lay flat, barren, uninterrupted—&lt;em&gt;and un-mastered by Europe&lt;/em&gt; as ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="european colonial possessions 1900" class="img-responsive" src="https://apworldunit5.weebly.com/uploads/7/6/7/6/76761401/701214.gif?880"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;N.B. By 1900, the majority of Latin American states, their own colonial history predominantly that of Spanish, Dutch and Portuguese imperialism, had already gained independence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, in 1904, why was this so significant? Among his esteemed and learned colleagues at the Royal Geographical Society, representing in turn the titans of contemporary global order, why was Mackinder so acutely preoccupied with the final "piece of the puzzle"—the "Heartland"—so influential in Europe's pre-Columbian history?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a barren steppe, the Heartland lacks the stone and timber necessary for road-making. As such, throughout the majority of history, it was best traversed in the same fashion as that of the Asiatic invaders: on lunky horse and camel. However, in 1904, a recent technology was poised to &lt;em&gt;radically&lt;/em&gt; alter this fact, to substantially accelerate the pace with which the Steppe could be crossed, to transform the perennial Steppe Invasion from a dainty pestle into an earth-fracturing pneumatic drill. This technology, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_rail_transport"&gt;introduced&lt;/a&gt; in Britain around 1830, was the &lt;em&gt;railroad&lt;/em&gt;, and the &lt;em&gt;steam-powered trains&lt;/em&gt; to which it played host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following graph shows the growing number of rail passengers per year at the time of Mackinder's writing, which we can understand as a proxy for the growing number of miles of railroad itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="rail passengers by year" class="img-responsive" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/15/GBR_rail_passengers_by_year_1830-2015.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Mackinder concludes, delivering his key insight as well as the Heartland Theory itself in one grand sweep:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A generation ago steam and the Suez canal appeared to have increased the mobility of sea-power relatively to land-power. Railways acted chiefly as feeders to ocean-going commerce. But trans-continental railways are now transmuting the conditions of land-power, and nowhere can they have such effect as in the closed heart-land of Euro-Asia, in vast areas of which neither timber nor accessible stone was available for road-making. Railways work the greater wonders in the steppe, because they directly replace horse and camel mobility, the road stage of development having here been omitted. [...] As we consider this rapid review of the broader currents of history, does not a certain persistence of geographical relationship become evident? Is not the pivot region of the world's politics that vast area of Euro-Asia which is inaccessible to ships, but in antiquity lay open to the horse-riding nomads, as is to-day about to be covered with a network of railways?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="geographical pivot" class="img-responsive" src="https://willwolf.io/images/mackinder-on-ai/geographical-pivot.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Zooming out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though Mackinder's thesis is specific to 20th century Continental Europe, I think there is a broader framework at play. Personally, I read Mackinder to be saying the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present day, there is a global hegemon. This hegemon is content, if haughty, with its place in the world. Modern history presented this hegemon with a task, a challenge, an "unclaimed space on which to plant its flags," and the hegemon did just that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not quite: there is still &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; space it failed to claim. And this particular space, as it goes, facilitated singular and outsized destruction in the past. So, hegemon beware!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is today a novel technology neatly poised to reify this destruction on a much grander scale than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this framework in mind, what might Mackinder write if he were alive today?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The United States&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past 100 years, the United States has transformed itself from a non-interventionist island nation of lofty ideals into a heavyweight champion of military might, economic preponderance, and cultural dominance at global scale. To wit, 1918 saw President Woodrow Wilson delivering his &lt;a href="https://www.theworldwar.org/learn/peace/fourteen-points"&gt;Fourteen Points&lt;/a&gt; touting "freedom of the seas and free trade and the concept of national self-determination," while 2020 America maintains ~1,000 &lt;a href="https://www.thenation.com/article/archive/the-us-has-military-bases-in-172-countries-all-of-them-must-close/"&gt;military bases&lt;/a&gt; in ~100 countries, controls ~30% of the &lt;a href="https://www.visualcapitalist.com/all-of-the-worlds-wealth-in-one-visualization/#:~:text=Leading%20the%20pack%20is%20the,share%20of%20the%20global%20total."&gt;world's wealth&lt;/a&gt;, and cannot count on &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2016/12/23/the-cia-says-russia-hacked-the-u-s-election-here-are-6-things-to-learn-from-cold-war-attempts-to-change-regimes/"&gt;seven sets of hands&lt;/a&gt; the number of times its CIA has &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Killing-Hope-C-I-Interventions-II-Updated/dp/1567512526"&gt;intervened in foreign countries&lt;/a&gt; since its &lt;a href="https://www.cia.gov/about-cia/history-of-the-cia"&gt;establishment in 1947&lt;/a&gt;. Though its detractors are harsh, and though President Donald Trump's foppishness and distinctly isolationist bent may indeed alter this course, the fact remains that the United States &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; Mackinder's unambiguous contemporary hegemon—his Continental Europe of 1904—eminently comfortable, if &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/02/07/opinion/sunday/western-society-decadence.html"&gt;decaying&lt;/a&gt;, in its gold-rimmed seat on top of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continental Europe achieved its own preponderance by winning the war of global &lt;em&gt;land&lt;/em&gt;: occupying—with lust, zeal and greed—as much of the map as it could throughout the Columbian era. In turn, the United States reached its current seat by winning the war of global &lt;em&gt;ideas&lt;/em&gt;, which Europe lost: from the brutal, hellish ruins of a 77-year Battle Royal from 1914 to 1991 between fascism, communism and free-market democracy—in other words, not over who gets what of an empty map, but how we live where we currently are in a map already full, encompassing the two World Wars and the Cold War—the United States and the ideas it represented emerged victorious, while Continental Europe fell to ruin. From then on, the United States became the global imperial much like the Columbian Europeans, patrolling the space of ideas with weapons and money—both as a beachhead-plus-lighthouse for the ideals of democracy, along with frequent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign_interventions_by_the_United_States#Post-Cold_War"&gt;foreign interventions&lt;/a&gt; to this effect—instead of the seas themselves, cementing its role as global hegemon in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The modern war of ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas the 20th century fought over what I will call "macro-ideology"—how nation-states should self-organize in the broadest of political, economic and social terms—2020 America is home to vicious wars over, in comparison, "micro-ideology": conduct in the workplace, gender identity and bias, police brutality, racial justice, who "belongs" where, and an infinity of other like topics that animate a sizable chunk of our current social discourse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this fight, people have taken to the street. To wit, the May 2020 murder of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Floyd"&gt;George Floyd&lt;/a&gt; at the hands of Minneapolis police officer Derek Chauvin sparked humungous, long-lasting protests around the country and world. In 2017, the day after Donald Trump's inauguration, the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_Women%27s_March"&gt;Women's March&lt;/a&gt; protesting his anti-women rhetoric became the largest single-day protest in U.S. history. Throughout the Trump presidency, white nationalist groups have variously assembled—the infamous 2017 Unite the Right rally in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unite_the_Right_rally"&gt;Charlottesville&lt;/a&gt; as the most prominent example—declaiming in fire and fury, well, who really knows—to much public attention and even &lt;a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-40980175"&gt;counter-protest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, for all of the issues over which we currently fight, do we not, as Ross Douthat writes in &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Decadent-Society-Became-Victims-Success/dp/1476785244"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Decadent Society&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, conduct the &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; of these battles on our &lt;em&gt;screens&lt;/em&gt; rather than in the streets themselves? Are the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sturmabteilung"&gt;Brownshirts&lt;/a&gt; of our time not smashing the heads of their adversaries in the public square, but instead patrolling the forums of Reddit and the "I don't know who needs to hear this; Thread 🧵:"'s of Twitter, throwing flame in the form of an ironic tweet at whoever disagrees? Has physical violence not largely been replaced by &lt;em&gt;reputational&lt;/em&gt; violence, i.e. our modern &lt;a href="https://www.dictionary.com/e/pop-culture/cancel-culture/#:~:text=Cancel%20culture%20refers%20to%20the,the%20form%20of%20group%20shaming."&gt;&lt;em&gt;cancel culture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;? For the &lt;em&gt;majority&lt;/em&gt; of Americans, is the intensity of our political beliefs &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; commensurate with our corresponding actions in &lt;a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=meatspace"&gt;"meatspace"&lt;/a&gt;? Or do we say these things to our like-minded friends, feel these things when we come home from work, and then, out for blood and looking to fight, we take to the internet for twenty minutes to throw a few punches and be punched right back, then ice cream, Netflix, and early to bed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protest and demonstration in the streets is not dead. However, in terms of dynamism, large-scale impact, and sheer number of combatants, the Internet truly is the preeminent battlefield of our time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The remaining space on the map&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the dust settled over the world in &lt;a href="https://history.state.gov/milestones/1989-1992/collapse-soviet-union#:~:text=On%20December%2025%2C%201991%2C%20the,the%20newly%20independent%20Russian%20state."&gt;1991&lt;/a&gt; following 77 brutal years of physical and psychological war over macro-ideology, the United States emerged on top, much like Mackinder's post-Columbian Europe following its own implicit victory—territorial and economic expansion unprecedented in history. Nevertheless, in our modern day, there exists a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; space on the map of human interaction that the United States has &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; conquered, the space where our current war for micro-ideology is largely waged, and, as it was ultimately a fight for ideology that felled the previous global powers, a space of critical importance. This space, of course, is the Internet: the Mackinderian Digital Heartland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The practical nature of battles online&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mackinder's dictum about the importance of the Central Asian heart-land stemmed from the impending technological revolution in its harmful potential: whereas the invaders used to crosse the Steppe on camel and horse—slowly, in other words—they would soon be racing under starry desert skies on steam-powered train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presently, ideological battles online take place with text, video and audio authored manually by humans; in other words, slowly! It is humans that write tweets and think-pieces to which other humans respond. It is humans that start digital media campaigns, create YouTube content, stoke the fires that lead to real-life demonstration and violence, and even coordinate large-scale protests themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what happens when a technology comes along that stands to turbo-charge the speed and chaos with which these battles take place? What happens when the text, video and audio that comprise these battles are created not by humans, but by &lt;em&gt;algorithms&lt;/em&gt;—unaccountable, indefatigable, at times sloppy, and brutally fast? Finally, what happens when human combatants, who we currently "eliminate" from battle via &lt;em&gt;reputational&lt;/em&gt; assassination, are replaced by algorithms that are immune to this deadliest weapon?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mackinder on artifical intelligence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 21st century Halford Mackinder would look at the deafening roll of artificial intelligence innovation in models that generate video, audio and language and be rightfully crapping his pants. Because simply, these models have the ability to do to our already-chaotic online debate not what trains, but 3D-printable intercontinental ballistic missiles, would have done for the Steppe Invaders of centuries past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this claim, we don't have to go much past the recent advent of &lt;a href="https://openai.com/blog/openai-api/"&gt;OpenAI's GPT-3&lt;/a&gt;, neatly explained in the following video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SboKeK6FFHQ" target="_blank" title="GPT-3 - explained in layman terms."&gt;&lt;img alt="Click me!" class="img-responsive" src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/SboKeK6FFHQ/0.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence, and borrowing from the video, "GPT-3 is an extremely sophisticated text predictor. A human gives it a chunk of text as input, and the model generates its best guess as to what the next chunk of text should be." In other words, and in terms of online battle, it reads what's written, and responds. However, crucially, whereas a human might reply to 1 or 2 posts over a 5-minute period, GPT-3 could create or reply to thousands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate the ability of these models, &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/8/16/21371049/gpt3-hacker-news-ai-blog"&gt;college student Liam Porr recently generated&lt;/a&gt; the following &lt;a href="https://adolos.substack.com/p/feeling-unproductive-maybe-you-should"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; using GPT-3. In effect, he fed a title and prompt (about human productivity) to the model, asked it for a few different drafts, selected the best one, edited it minimally, then hit publish. The post itself quickly earned the top-spot on vaunted &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;, seemingly on the merits of its content alone. Take a look and see for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, what happens when our online battles are fueled by such &lt;em&gt;high-quality content generated by models like GPT-3 at warp speed?&lt;/em&gt; In a world whose news cycle already changes by the hour? In which social media is already such a dominant force?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, your guess, and Mackinder's guess, are as good as mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to control the Digital Heartland, and what's at stake&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implicit in Mackinder's admonition is that control of the Central Asian Heartland means the same type of control with which European then-empires came to dominate the rest of the world: economic, political or outright military dominion (and to wit, this is in effect what Hitler then tried to do). Unfortunately, he neglects to offer more specific guidance—especially with respect to the impending explosion in railroad construction in which he places so much concern. With this in mind, how might a 21st century Mackinder encourage the United States to "control" the Digital Heartland? By crafting then backing the internet's dominant ideological current, a la victory in the Cold War? By creating a monopoly on the internet's infrastructure and data, i.e. controlling the servers on which online war is waged, and owning the data that it generates? By training, employing and overseeing the bulk of the researchers that build the artificial intelligence itself? Or perhaps by gaining ownership over the specific platforms, like Twitter and Reddit, on which combatants clash?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the answer is not necessarily clear, and a deeper analysis of this question is the subject of a future post. Nonetheless, it is clear that the eventual conclusion of this war—the "1991" of our current age—has the real potential to spawn some sort of parallel, supranational organization or hegemony rooted more in a sense of identity and ideological affiliation, in which your figurative "digital passport" does not have the name of a sovereign physical territory embroidered on its front, but instead, a way of thought or belief picked from amongst the micro-ideological multiplex that is the modern internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A closing warning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As 1904 Continental Europe stood at, in his view, the exit of the Columbian era, Mackinder leaves us with one final warning about the practical reality of the coming world order. Whereas pre-Columbian Europe was "pent into a narrow region and threatened by external barbarism," and Columbian Europe was characterized by "the expansion of Europe against almost negligible resistances," a now post-Columbian Europe will take an altogether different hue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the present time forth, in the post-Columbian age, we shall again have to deal with a closed political system, and none the less that it will be one of worldwide scope. Every explosion of social forces, instead of being dissipated in a surrounding circuit of unknown space and barbaric chaos, will be sharply re-echoed from the far side of the globe, and weak elements in the political and economic organism of the world will be shattered in consequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, his second sentence is utterly jarring: if Mackinder worries thus about the consequences of an "explosion of social forces" in a "closed political system," what would he say about combat on our modern internet—in which social forces, quite literally, can reach and ignite the remotest corners of the world &lt;em&gt;minutes&lt;/em&gt; after their birth? In which further explosions of these forces are, as the military-industrial complex is to traditional warfare, bolstered by the advertising industry, wherein wealthy and powerful executives have a direct incentive to throw kerosene on the flames? And how would he feel about the fact that, in a broad sense, this fiery battlefield is increasingly hard to leave—as we learn more, bank more, socialize more, and work more online?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On fatalism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase Robert Kaplan in Chapter 9 of &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Revenge-Geography-Coming-Conflicts-Against/dp/0812982223"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Revenge of Geography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, "though Mackinder was often attacked as an arch-deterministic, a charge not wholly unfair, no doubt, owing to the fact that geography was his subject, and geography itself can by its very nature be deterministic, Mackinder was no mere fatalist: ultimately, he believed that geography and the environment could be overcome, but only if we treat those subjects with the greatest knowledge and respect."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, a 21st century Mackinder might say that the technology that we currently build does not have to invite an invasion of the Huns. It does not have to poison social order. And finally, as artificial intelligence combatants are increasingly whisked off to wage internet war, he'd hope that we don't inadvertently burn it all down before we get much further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Credit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to Abishur Prakash for reviewing an earlier draft of this piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional references&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Are We on the Road to Civilisation Collapse?” BBC Future, BBC, www.bbc.com/future/article/20190218-are-we-on-the-road-to-civilisation-collapse. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chan, Amy. “Behind the Lines: When Empires Collapse.” HistoryNet, HistoryNet, 15 May 2017, www.historynet.com/behind-lines-empires-collapse.htm. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holland, Tom. Why Empires Fall: from Ancient Rome to Putin's Russia, 23 May 2014, www.newstatesman.com/politics/2014/05/why-empires-fall-ancient-rome-putins-russia. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mackinder, Halford J. “The Geographical Pivot of History.” The Geographical Journal, vol. 23, no. 4, 1904, p. 421., doi:10.2307/1775498. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mihir Shukla, Automation Anywhere. “The Role of Automation in the Aging Workforce.” VentureBeat, VentureBeat, 19 Apr. 2018, venturebeat.com/2018/04/19/the-role-of-automation-in-the-aging-workforce/. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why Do Empires Decline?” Quora, www.quora.com/Why-do-empires-decline. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry><entry><title>Soft Power in the Age of Generative Models</title><link href="https://willwolf.io/2020/03/12/soft-power-in-the-age-of-generative-models/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-12T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-12T08:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Will Wolf</name></author><id>tag:willwolf.io,2020-03-12:/2020/03/12/soft-power-in-the-age-of-generative-models/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What happens when a post-Trump, reputationally-bruised United States, and improved generative models (the technology behind "deepfakes") collide head-on?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nations exert influence in two key ways: hard power, and soft power. Hard power is &lt;a href="https://www.history.com/topics/world-war-ii/bombing-of-hiroshima-and-nagasaki"&gt;dropping the atomic bomb&lt;/a&gt; on Hiroshima and Nagasaki during World War II, compelling the Japanese to surrender. Conversely, soft power is building American libraries in foreign universities, placing American films in foreign theaters, and sending &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peace_Corps"&gt;United States Peace Corps&lt;/a&gt; volunteers to rural communities worldwide, compelling a favorable image of our country abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, hard power is to influence via economic and military violence; soft power is to influence via &lt;em&gt;attraction.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Soft power through media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key subset of soft power is that delivered through media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, during the Franco-Prussian War, the French dropped leaflets over enemy territory by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airborne_leaflet_propaganda"&gt;airborne balloon&lt;/a&gt; touting the mutual benefits of ceasefire. During World War I, all parties dropped such leaflets by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airborne_leaflet_propaganda#First_World_War"&gt;airplane&lt;/a&gt;. In World War II, the Nazis pioneered the use of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio_propaganda#Nazi_Germany"&gt;radio&lt;/a&gt; as a propaganda machine. Finally, in 1969, the Americans live-broadcast Neil Armstrong’s moon landing to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cwZb2mqId0A"&gt;television&lt;/a&gt; screens worldwide, showcasing the "derring-do and genius of American ingenuity, and putting one over the Soviets at the same time."&lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:7"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, such media is more numerous and diverse: American shows on Netflix, American music on Spotify, American “influencers” on YouTube, Hollywood movies and more—all distributed globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The cost of media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of media can be split into two broad camps: creation and distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the days of leaflets by balloons, the marginal cost of distribution has become extremely cheap. Today, Trump tweets, and his words instantaneously appear on the timelines of his 75 million followers. Were he to have 150 instead, the additional cost of reaching these additional 75 would be, practically speaking, nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the creation of this media itself remains a wholly manual exercise. To create a news broadcast, humans write scripts, set the stage, select the costumes, apply makeup, and read the news itself. Furthermore, creating twice as many news broadcasts costs, crucially, roughly twice as much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dwindling marginal cost of its distribution makes soft power media efficient and appealing. However, it is the “creation bottleneck” that stands in the way of true scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Generative models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generative models are those that empower &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deepfake"&gt;“deepfakes.”&lt;/a&gt; They are algorithms that generate realistic &lt;a href="https://thispersondoesnotexist.com/"&gt;images&lt;/a&gt; (refresh this link for more), &lt;a href="https://medium.com/syncedreview/deepmind-dvd-gan-impressive-step-toward-realistic-video-synthesis-12027d942e53"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://openai.com/blog/musenet/"&gt;audio&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://talktotransformer.com/"&gt;text&lt;/a&gt;, or other types of rich media. Presently, generative models excel in creating art, music, literature, news reports, and textiles. &lt;a href="https://news.microsoft.com/apac/features/much-more-than-a-chatbot-chinas-xiaoice-mixes-ai-with-emotions-and-wins-over-millions-of-fans/"&gt;Microsoft’s Xiaoice&lt;/a&gt;, a multi-purpose &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chatbot"&gt;chatbot&lt;/a&gt; (which currently dialogs with over 660 million registered users), pulls all this off and more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Xiaoice’s framework is learning to write literature as well as compose and perform songs. Last year she published a book of poems and helps her followers write their own. She can sing her own songs in styles based on existing popular performers. There are plans to release an album of pop tunes soon. And she is able to author tailor-made stories for children and reads them out in voices suited to each of the characters she has created.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;She’s painting images based on keywords and other inputs. She’s also gone into mainstream media as a host of dozens of TV and radio programs that are broadcast across China. She reads news stories and provides commentary. And, she is generating multiple reports based on information from China’s financial markets and used by investors and traders who subscribe to Wind, a major financial information service.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In short, generative models &lt;strong&gt;automate&lt;/strong&gt; the creation of media itself—smashing the “creation bottleneck” outright.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coming soon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, generative models succeed at tasks like: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PCBTZh41Ris"&gt;transferring dance moves&lt;/a&gt; from professionals to amateurs, &lt;a href="https://github.com/elliottwu/sText2Image"&gt;translating pencil sketches&lt;/a&gt; to high-resolution images with the guidance of text, and making Obama lip sync the words of American actor Jordan Peele.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cQ54GDm1eL0" title="Click me!"&gt;&lt;img alt="Click me!" class="img-responsive" src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/cQ54GDm1eL0/0.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These feats are impressive. However, to achieve widespread impact, these algorithms must allow for more “control” over the media they create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, consider a system that, given English text, instantaneously generates a video of this text being recited in an arbitrary language. To be truly effective as a soft power tool, this system must ultimately operate as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System&lt;/strong&gt;: “What kind of video would you like?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User&lt;/strong&gt;: “I’d like a video of the President reciting the uploaded text. I'd like him to speak slowly, be wearing green US Army fatigues, and be seated in front of a blue Boeing CH-47 Chinook. Make me two, actually: one in Farsi, the other in Greek.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System&lt;/strong&gt;: “Coming right up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Such generative models are not quite here. However, given the speed at which this &lt;a href="http://www.arxiv-sanity.com/search?q=video+generation"&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; moves, they will reliably arrive within 5 years.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The United States used to invest in soft power institutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, the United States invested substantially in soft power institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During World War I, Woodrow Wilson established the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committee_on_Public_Information"&gt;Committee on Public Information&lt;/a&gt;, which ultimately trafficked in outright propaganda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During World War II, Roosevelt established the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_diplomacy_of_the_United_States"&gt;Division of Cultural Relations&lt;/a&gt; and Office of Inter-American Affairs in response to fascist propaganda in Latin America. Following the bombing of Pearl Harbor, the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voice_of_America"&gt;Voice of America&lt;/a&gt;—a globally-distributed radio broadcast of non-military promotional content—the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Office_of_War_Information"&gt;Office of War Information&lt;/a&gt;—distributing media like “newspapers, posters, photographs, films”&lt;sup id="fnref:8"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:8"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to civilian communities abroad—and the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_of_Strategic_Services"&gt;Office of Strategic Services&lt;/a&gt;—the predecessor to the CIA—were all established as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Cold War, the United States flexed its “peacetime” soft power muscle, establishing myriad organizations to promote international cultural and educational exchanges, including the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fulbright_Program"&gt;Fulbright Program&lt;/a&gt; in 1947 and the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_diplomacy_of_the_United_States#U.S._Information_Agency_(USIA)"&gt;United States Information Agency&lt;/a&gt; (USIA) in 1953.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dwindling interest and opportunity missed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the Cold War, however, American soft power institutions began to slowly decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1999, the USIA was absorbed into the US State Department; its staff, and budget for key projects, were cut roughly in half.&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; “From 1995 to 2001, academic and cultural exchanges dropped from 45,000 to 29,000 annually, and many accessible cultural centers and libraries were closed.”&lt;sup id="fnref2:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Finally, “while government-funded radio broadcasts reached between 70 and 80 percent of the populace of Eastern Europe during the Cold War, around year 2000, a mere 2 percent of Arabs heard the VOA.”&lt;sup id="fnref3:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, the United States has a largely &lt;a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/2017/01/trump-foreign-policy-isolationsim-america-first-allies-nato-trans-pacific-partnership/"&gt;isolationist president&lt;/a&gt; in Donald Trump. Since the beginning of his term, American soft power has fallen globally according to the Portland &lt;a href="https://softpower30.com/"&gt;Soft Power 30&lt;/a&gt;. Trump himself is unconcerned with others actively &lt;a href="https://www.rollcall.com/2018/09/25/world-leaders-laugh-as-trump-boasts-of-accomplishments/"&gt;laughing&lt;/a&gt; at him and his country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2018, Statista estimates that there were 1.67 billion "pay TV households" worldwide.&lt;sup id="fnref:9"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:9"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; By 2019, they estimate that half of private households had a computer.&lt;sup id="fnref:10"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:10"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Finally, Pew Research estimates that "more than 5 billion people have mobile devices, and over half of these connections are smartphones."&lt;sup id="fnref:11"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:11"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_Age"&gt;Information Age&lt;/a&gt;, a dwindling interest in soft power institutions is a &lt;strong&gt;major&lt;/strong&gt; opportunity missed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent article, Joseph Nye, the Harvard professor who coined the term “soft power” itself, neatly summarizes this phenomenon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“U.S. President Donald Trump’s administration has shown little interest in public diplomacy. And yet public diplomacy—a government’s efforts to communicate directly with other countries’ publics—is one of the key instruments policymakers use to generate soft power, and the current information revolution makes such instruments more important than ever.”&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A renewed interest in soft power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly impactful generative models, and Trump’s exit from office, will soon collide head-on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, the United States—with its blemished reputation, exorbitant military budget&lt;sup id="fnref:12"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:12"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, longstanding technical leadership&lt;sup id="fnref:13"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:13"&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and forever proactive drive—will be sitting on transformative media tech and a clear-cut mission: rebuild its image at home and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To this effect, I predict that the United States will soon make a concerted investment in generative models for soft power at true scale.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what this might look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Soft power through media, in the age of generative models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two keys areas which generative models will impact are state-to-public, and state-to-individual media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;State-to-public media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current examples of state-to-public soft power media, like Presidential addresses to the American people, English-language CNN news broadcasts to foreign viewers, and front-line conflict reporting will see their use both quickened and expanded by generative models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presently, Presidential addresses happen once every few weeks or months. Conversely, Donald Trump writes on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; hourly. With generative models, the next President will &lt;em&gt;instantaneously&lt;/em&gt; generate videos of herself reciting the tweet instead. Americans at large devour the President's tweets; if a generated video legitimately looks and sounds just like her, they’re likely to devour it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sponsorship deals, like &lt;a href="https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/14314807/lebron-james-signs-life-deal-nike"&gt;Lebrons’ lifetime appointment&lt;/a&gt; with Nike, will crucially expand to include the right to generate content with the athlete’s likeness. Politicians will travel less to campaign; instead, they’ll send generated holograms—of them, their spouses, their key supporters—to campaign instead—each one personalized to the venue in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a generative model will be trained to ingest footage of world events—for example, the &lt;a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/09/14/middleeast/yemen-houthi-rebels-drone-attacks-saudi-aramco-intl/index.html"&gt;attack&lt;/a&gt; on the Saudi oil refinery—and produce text describing what happened. This text will then be used to generate a news report. Humans won’t be on the front line to capture this footage either; why not send a drone instead?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;State-to-individual media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft’s Xiaoice demonstrates the enormous traction of personalized chatbots. From here, the jump to state-built, propaganda-(subtly)-infused chatbots is small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the public distrusts governments; to this effect, humanitarian missions are typically run by NGOs. As such, states will deploy these chatbots on behalf of related entities: tourism boards, online universities, cultural centers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, current state-to-individual media is largely &lt;em&gt;unidirectional&lt;/em&gt;: media is sent from the former to the latter, and rarely vice versa. Chatbots powered by generative models, however, will solicit &lt;em&gt;feedback&lt;/em&gt; from their viewer in a personalized way; for example, “Are you enjoying this media? What do you like about American schools as compared to your own? What do you think about democracy?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same way that the Chinese government &lt;em&gt;passively&lt;/em&gt; learns about its citizens by &lt;a href="http://harvardpolitics.com/world/wechat-the-people-technology-and-social-control-in-china/"&gt;monitoring WeChat data&lt;/a&gt;, generative models will &lt;em&gt;actively solicit information&lt;/em&gt; re the efficacy of their soft power plays. Then, like a savvy marketer, they’ll double down on the stuff that works best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a century, states have exercised soft power through media. Throughout, the marginal cost of distributing this media has trended towards zero. Conversely, to date, the marginal cost of its creation remains high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generative models are a powerful technology which trend the latter towards zero as well. They're here and they work. However, to be truly impactful, there's still a short ways to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 5 years' time, a dazed, reputationally-bruised United States, and robust, flexible, practical generative models, will collide head-on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At this point, soft power media—and human politics in general—are likely to change forever.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Credit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to Abishur Prakash for reviewing earlier drafts of this piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brands, Hal. “Not Even Trump Can Obliterate America's Soft Power.” Bloomberg.com, Bloomberg, www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2018-01-18/not-even-trump-can-obliterate-america-s-soft-power. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chakravarti, Sudeshna. Soft Power: The Culture Weapon in The Cold War and South Asia. www.culturaldiplomacy.org/academy/content/pdf/participant-papers/academy/Sudeshna-Khasnobis-Soft-Power-The-Culture-Weapon-in-The-Cold-War-and-South-Asia.pdf. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khandelwal, Aakash. “Economics of Digital Goods.” LinkedIn SlideShare, 23 Nov. 2016, www.slideshare.net/aakashkhandelwal921/economics-of-digital-goods. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nye, Joseph S. “No, President Trump: You've Weakened America's Soft Power.” The New York Times, The New York Times, 25 Feb. 2020, www.nytimes.com/2020/02/25/opinion/trump-soft-power.html. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shah, Ritula. “Is US Monopoly on the Use of Soft Power at an End?” BBC News, BBC, 19 Nov. 2014, www.bbc.com/news/world-29536648. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nye, Joseph S. Soft Power: the Means to Success in World Politics. Knowledge World, 2012. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref3:6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harris, Paul. “Man on the Moon: Moment of Greatness That Defined the American Century.” The Guardian, Guardian News and Media, 25 Aug. 2012, www.theguardian.com/science/2012/aug/25/man-moon-american-century. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:7" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“United States Office of War Information.” Wikipedia, Wikimedia Foundation, 7 Jan. 2020, en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Office_of_War_Information. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:8" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watson, Amy. “TV Households Worldwide.” Statista, 4 Dec. 2019, www.statista.com/statistics/268695/number-of-tv-households-worldwide/. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:9" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:10"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statista Research Department. “How Many People Have Access to a Computer 2018.” Statista, 2 Mar. 2020, www.statista.com/statistics/748551/worldwide-households-with-computer/. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:10" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:11"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silver, Laura. “Smartphone Ownership Is Growing Rapidly Around the World, but Not Always Equally.” Pew Research Center's Global Attitudes Project, Pew Research Center, 30 Dec. 2019, www.pewresearch.org/global/2019/02/05/smartphone-ownership-is-growing-rapidly-around-the-world-but-not-always-equally/. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:11" title="Jump back to footnote 11 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:12"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cancian, Mark F. “U.S. Military Forces in FY 2020: The Strategic and Budget Context.” U.S. Military Forces in FY 2020: The Strategic and Budget Context | Center for Strategic and International Studies, 12 Mar. 2020, www.csis.org/analysis/us-military-forces-fy-2020-strategic-and-budget-context?gclid=CjwKCAjwgbLzBRBsEiwAXVIygLkZlNLc3zV8EVVhPPwjOoqrUoQ4kjTeaTHN5vFktRWET2wsnHCwRhoCm2QQAvD_BwE. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:12" title="Jump back to footnote 12 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:13"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Report Shows United States Leads in Science and Technology as China Rapidly Advances.” ScienceDaily, ScienceDaily, 24 Jan. 2018, www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2018/01/180124113951.htm. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:13" title="Jump back to footnote 13 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry><entry><title>On Saudi Drone Strikes and Adversarial AI</title><link href="https://willwolf.io/2019/09/22/saudi-drone-strikes-and-adversarial-ai/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-22T08:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-22T08:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Will Wolf</name></author><id>tag:willwolf.io,2019-09-22:/2019/09/22/saudi-drone-strikes-and-adversarial-ai/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In world of weaponized drones piloted by algorithms, what new strategic opportunities arise?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, Houthi rebels—a militant political group in Yemen—claimed credit for exploding an oil refinery in Saudi Arabia. The explosion was the work of a missile, fired from a drone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the group responsible is closely allied with Iran—and to wit, the American government does declaim Iran as responsible for facilitating the strike itself—it is by all accounts a non-state actor, notable for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the cost of full-scale war increases due to, at a trivial minimum, the strength of weapons available, small, “surgical” operations become more common. This attack falls in directly with this trend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You do not have to be the state to desire to affect world politics. As weapons become more potent, and the “density” of potential targets—population density, in the case of traditional military offensives, or density of nodes in an information-sharing network, in the case of cyber offensives, as two examples—increases, the ability to affect outsized change increases as well. As such, incentives for, and frequency of, strategic action from non-state actors will likely continue to rise—this being yet another example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The technologies required to effectuate the attack in question are increasingly easy to obtain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, last week’s strike is yet another example of an isolated punch by a non-state actor with technologies (drones, at a minimum) ultimately available in the public domain. Moving forward, it seems safe to expect more of the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enter machine learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout history, much of war has been about destroying the enemy’s stuff. There are many ways to do this—each involving a distinct set of tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this effect, drones are particularly interesting: they allow for precise, close-proximity strikes, without risking the lives of the aggressors. Presently, the majority of such drones are piloted remotely by humans; moving forward, they—in conceptual step with, say, self-driving cars—will pilot themselves, allowing for larger and larger deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, engineers will equip drones with cameras, and machine learning algorithms that make the drone’s operational and tactical decisions conditional on what these cameras show. As such, the defensive objective is still, as per usual, thwart the aggressor; &lt;strong&gt;however, the aggressor is now the machine learning algorithms controlling the aggressor’s tech.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For drones, what do these algorithms look like? How can they be thwarted? What risks and opportunities do they imply for the defense of critical infrastructure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;While these questions might seem futuristic, that future is indeed approaching fast.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The supervised classification model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin the discussion, let’s look at the basic paradigm by which self-driving cars operate: the supervised classification model, which works as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineers collect a large amount of “labeled data” in the form of &lt;code&gt;(cameras_images, what_the_driver_did)&lt;/code&gt; pairs. This data is considered “labeled,” as each input, &lt;code&gt;cameras_images&lt;/code&gt;, is coupled with an output, &lt;code&gt;what_the_driver_did&lt;/code&gt;. An example of the former might be 360-degree images of a curving, barren road in Arizona; the latter, i.e. what the driver did in this moment in time, might be: depress the gas pedal by five degrees, and rotate the steering wheel counter-clockwise by seven.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Teach” a computer to, given photographic input, predict the correct driver action to be taken.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roughly speaking, a self-piloting drone would not be different: it’d require equivalent labeled data from human-controlled flights, on which a supervised classification model would be trained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A likely progression of offensive drone tech&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weaponized drone deployment will likely progress as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy drones that pilot themselves; however, “finish” decisions are still executed by humans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy drones that pilot themselves; “finish” decisions are executed by the drone—when it is extremely confident in its choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy swarms of drones that work together to more swiftly and efficiently achieve the aforementioned—attacking, exchanging data, self-sacrificing optimally, etc. throughout their attack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In a brave new world of machine-learned aggressors, what new opportunities for defense arise?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adversarial examples in machine learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adversarial examples for supervised image classification models are inputs, i.e. images, whose pixels have been perturbed in a way imperceptible to a human eye, yet cause the classifier to change its prediction entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; looks as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="png" class="img-responsive" src="https://willwolf.io/images/saudi-adversarial/panda-adversarial-example.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the classifier is 57.7% confident that the image contains a panda; after adding noise, resulting in the image on the right—still, inarguably, a panda, to the human eye—the classifier has now changed its prediction to "gibbon" with 99.3% confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As such, knowledge of the data on which an aggressive drone was trained gives unique opportunity to algorithmically design adversarial examples, like the above, that confuse its classifier aboard.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concrete opportunities would include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At “find”&lt;/strong&gt;: defensive lasers pointed at critical infrastructure dynamically perturb, by just a few pixels, its appearance, tricking the drone into thinking it has not found what it actually has.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At “fix”&lt;/strong&gt;: these lasers dynamically concoct sequences of perturbations, tricking the drone into thinking its target is moving erratically when it’s actually still.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At “finish”&lt;/strong&gt;: adversarial examples make the drone believe its strike would, put simply, cause more damage than it intends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As adversarial examples are, once more, built from real examples, perturbed minimally, in a way imperceptible to the human eye, they are in fact difficult to, even a priori, teach our classifier to ignore. Said differently, well-designed adversarial examples are extremely effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Out-of-distribution data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning algorithms are notoriously bad at “knowing what they don’t know.” Said differently, these algorithms only learn to make decisions about the type of data on which they’re trained. Were a classification model piloting a drone to be presented with an image of an ice-cream cone, it would, barring careful design, attempt to make a decision about this data all the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world of autonomous fly-and-finish drones, one would hope that its finish decisions are taken with extreme care. Fundamentally, this dovetails quickly into the notion of “out-of-distribution” data, i.e. data that the classifier knows it has not seen before, and about which it therefore neglects to make a prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As such, insight into the data on which an enemy’s system was trained naturally implies “defense by what’s different”&lt;/strong&gt;: show the drone images you know that it hasn’t seen before, and thereby increase its uncertainty around the decision at hand—buying time, and keeping your stuff in tact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning optimal defense via reinforcement learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinforcement_learning"&gt;Reinforcement learning&lt;/a&gt;, though exceedingly powerful, and often overhyped, is a relatively simple idea: given an environment and its state, try an action, observe a reward, and repeat the actions that give high rewards; additionally, periodically explore new actions you’ve never tried before just to see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reinforcement learning, or RL, requires vast amounts of data. As such, as a point of “meta defensive strategy”, trying out different types of adversarial-machine-learning attacks against a drone, seeing which work best, then repeating the best performers, while plausible in theory, would not work in practice if one drone approaches your one oil refinery but once a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This said, swarms of drones might change the game; &lt;em&gt;what if, in 20 years, Houthi militants deployed one autonomous, armed drone for every square mile of Saudi territory?&lt;/em&gt; And what if we could simulate this scenario a priori, and learn how to optimally defend against the swarm?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, you'd require:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A heavy investment into sensors&lt;/strong&gt;, on all of: the infrastructure you’re trying to protect, atmospheric conditions in which the drones are flying, tools to monitor the drones’ speeds and movements, etc. In other words, any and all technologies that capture the state of the environment, and the rewards, to as granular level of detail as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simulation environments.&lt;/strong&gt; In certain RL problems, this one potentially included, one has the delicious ability to generate data from which the algorithm can learn—by letting it play games with itself. &lt;a href="https://deepmind.com/blog/article/alphago-zero-starting-scratch"&gt;AlphaGo Zero&lt;/a&gt; is one famous such example. Learning to optimally defend against a swarm of drones might fit the bit as well: deploy thousands of your own into a broad swath of desert, instruct them to “capture your flag”, then let your defensive systems get to work: taking actions, observing the subsequent reward—“Did I divert the drone away from my flag?”; “Did the drone hesitate more than usual before acting?”; etc.—and repeat those actions that work best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the years roll forward, machine learning algorithms will continue to direct more and more of our most critical systems—financial markets, healthcare, transportation, and alas—the offensive technologies of political groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wit, an understanding of the workings of these algorithms sheds light on the new risks these systems will introduce, and the new strategic opportunities that will thereafter arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodfellow, I., Shlens, J., Szegedy, C. (2014). Explaining and Harnessing Adversarial Examples https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.6572 &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Thumbnail) “Adversarial AI: As New Attack Vector Opens, Researchers Aim to Defend Against It.” DataProtectionCenter.com - Tech and Security, 17 Apr. 2018, dataprotectioncenter.com/malware/adversarial-ai-as-new-attack-vector-opens-researchers-aim-to-defend-against-it/. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry><entry><title>Artificial Intelligence and Geopolitics</title><link href="https://willwolf.io/2019/09/21/ai-and-geopolitics/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-21T21:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-21T21:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Will Wolf</name></author><id>tag:willwolf.io,2019-09-21:/2019/09/21/ai-and-geopolitics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm beginning to write about the intersection of artificial intelligence and geopolitics.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Machine learning and artificial intelligence have long been passions; to date, I've spent many years—my entire professional career included—developing relevant expertise. This has been the historical focus of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I've been reading heavily in other areas as well: history, political theory, strategy, economics and geography; geopolitics, in sum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geopolitics of yesterday—the subject of my reading—has its experts and central themes: collective security, nuclear armament, and oil, to name a few. Conversely, the geopolitics of tomorrow will take form from entirely new ideas; chief among them: artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, I plan to merge the two: to suffuse, through writing, my exploration of the former with my expertise in the latter. &lt;strong&gt;Specifically, I'll connect deep, technical knowledge of AI algorithms, as well as the likely implications of their widespread use, to the risks—and opportunities—that AI will bring to the geopolitics of tomorrow.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My writing will be objective, i.e. devoid of overt political bias. My intended audience is non-technical, i.e. geopolitics-first. Your comments—especially with respect to my evolving understanding of geopolitics itself—are encouraged as always.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="geopolitics"></category></entry></feed>